Guide to the William Mahone Papers, 1853-1895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Mahone papers 1853-1895
Mahone, William, 1826-1895
110.9 linear feet Extent: 100,000 items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00836
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Mahone Papers were placed on deposit in the Manuscript Department in 1930 and donated to Duke University in 1985 and 1986.
Biographical Note
1826, Dec. 1 Born Monroe, Southhampton Co., Va.
1847 Graduated from Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Va.
1850 Became Assistant Engineer of the Orange and Alexandria Railroad
1852 Became Chief Engineer, Fredericksburg and Valley Plank Road Company
1855 Married Otelia Butler
1861 Became President and Chief Engineer of the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad
1861 Commissioned Brigadier General in the Confederate Army
1863 Elected to the Virginia State Senate
1864 Commanded unit known as "Mahone's Brigade" at the Battle of the Petersburg Crater
1865 Simultaneously became President of both the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad and the South Side Railroad
1870 Created the privately owned Atlantic, Mississippi, and Ohio Railroad (AMandO)
1877 Defeated in seeking the Virginia Democratic gubernatorial nomination
1879 Organized and assumed leadership of the Readjuster Party in Virginia
1880 Elected to the United States Senate and pledged his allegiance to the Republican Party
1882 Became Chairman of the U.S. Senate Committee on Agriculture
1886 Ran unsuccessfully for reelection to the United States Senate
1889 Ran unsuccessfully for Governor of Virginia on the Republican ticket
1895, Oct. 8 Died in Washington, D.C. Buried in Petersburg, Va., where the Daughters of the Confederacy erected a monument to him
Collection Overview
The papers of William Mahone span the period 1853 to 1895, with the bulk of the material dating from 1876 to 1892. The collection consists of copies of letters written by Mahone to others, incoming letters to Mahone, subject files on a variety of topics, clippings, and scrapbooks, but primarily focuses on Mahone's railroad and political interests. There is a great deal of overlap of topics between the different series in the collection; thus information concerning Mahone's political and railroad interests is repeated in the different series.
Mahone's involvement in the railroad business dates from 1850 when he became the Assistant Engineer of the Orange and Alexandria Railroad. While there is information about several of the railroads in which Mahone held positions, including both the Orange and Alexandria and the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroads, the bulk of the material concerning railroads is related to the Atlantic, Mississippi, and Ohio Railroad (AMandO). There are both financial and legal papers concerning the AMandO after it ran into financial difficulties in 1873 following the economic panic of that year. Included is correspondence with two Englishmen, John Collinson, who helped Mahone finance a loan to buy the AMandO in 1870, and W. H. Chase, who tried to assist Mahone in saving the railroad. Controversies surrounding the consolidation of railroads in the United States and more particularly in Virginia during the mid to late 19th century are also well documented in the collection.
The bulk of the collection deals with Mahone's political interests and activities. The collection traces the rise of the Readjuster movement in Virginia in the late 1870s, due largely to the efforts of Mahone; Mahone's allegiance to the Republican Party once he was elected to the Senate in 1880; his efforts to build a well organized political machine in Virginia; and finally the loss of support both for Mahone and for the Republican Party in Virginia in the late 1880s.
A central issue in the Readjuster movement was the state's debt, which kept taxes at a high level and almost destroyed the new public school system. The readjusters insisted that the changed conditions of the post-bellum period necessitated the readjustment of the debt. Raising the spectre of class antagonism, Mahone was able to appeal to both poor whites and blacks in order to unite them in a movement of self-interest and reform. This led to the organization of the state-wide Readjuster Party in 1878.
The Readjuster Party won control of the Virginia legislature in 1879 and gained the governorship in 1881 with the election of William E. Cameron. The new party scaled down the debt in the Riddleberger Bill of 1882, enacted laws in social and economic arenas that were of interest to the masses, and, led by Mahone, apportioned governmental offices among the party's leaders. However, in 1883 and thereafter the Readjusters were unable to capture the state legislature or governorship again, although sometimes they lost only narrowly.
Clearly shown through the collection is Mahone's emphasis on organizing the cause of the Readjusters. The focus on organization, including the canvassing of voters before elections, is evident in Mahone's campaigns for the Senate in 1880 and 1886 and for governor of Virginia in 1889. Many of the papers deal with appointing canvassers, creating clubs that would encourage participation in the political process, targeting particular groups to be canvassed such as blacks and "mild" Democrats, making sure political speeches were made in the various precincts, and finding out who had not paid their head-tax and then arranging to have the tax paid. One key element was the Richmond Whig in which Mahone had a financial and editorial interest and which became the official organ of the Readjuster movement.
After Mahone was elected to the United States Senate, he had to choose whether his allegiance would be to the Democrats or Republicans. Once he had aligned himself with the Republicans, Virginia was sometimes viewed as having broken the Solid South, that is, Virginia was seen as one state in the South where Republicans could be elected. Both Virginia and Mahone served as role models for politicians in other southern states who wanted to foster the growth of the Republican Party.
While the collection primarily relates to local and state political matters in Virginia, there are scattered letters in the collection from other areas of the country where the Republican Party was being promoted. There are several letters from William M. Burwell from New Orleans, 1880 to 1884, asking for guidance and giving progress reports on the status of the Republican Party in Louisiana. A letter (1883, March 15) from James T. Beach, Secretary of the Missouri State Republican Committee, relates to his efforts to create a National Cooperative Organization. One of its goals was to secure equal civil and political rights for a free vote.
Mahone was appointed Chair of the United States Senate Committee on Agriculture in 1882 and served on the Committee on Naval Affairs, the Committee on Post-offices and Post-roads, and the Committee on Education and Labor. Evidence of his work on these committees is best shown in the Letterbooks, Correspondence, and Subject Files. It is in the appointment of persons to positions, however, where Mahone's influence is most clearly documented. Requests for patronage positions, particularly in the Post Office, dominate the constituent correspondence. Other letters requested that particular post offices be closed or opened.
Other departments to which persons sought appointment included the Government Printing Office, the Norfolk Navy Yard, the Navy Department, the Treasury Department, and the Internal Revenue Service. Included in both the Correspondence and the Subject Files (Politics: Appointments) series are recommendations, requests and petitions for persons seeking positions.
One incident documented in the collection is a riot that occurred in Danville, Va., on November 3, 1883, three days before the Virginia state elections. Under the Readjuster legislature, blacks held a number of governmental offices in Danville. The Democrats opposed the appointment of blacks and dubbed it "Mahoneism." It is difficult today to pinpoint the origin of the violence that occurred or trace its progress, but as a result of it, several blacks and whites died. Readjusters contended the uprising had been provoked by Democrats for campaign purposes. They also blamed their loss of a majority in the state legislature on the Danville Riot. The collection includes eyewitness accounts of the incident which are located in the Subject Files.
The collection also includes much information about voters and voting patterns down to the precinct level in Virginia during the 1880s. The files relating to election frauds, which date from 1882 to 1889, provide yet another perspective on voting concerns. These files contain standardized forms and letters reporting voting irregularities. The majority of the documented frauds are from 1889 when Mahone lost his bid for governor. There were some who believed that had voting irregularities not occurred, Mahone would have been elected governor in 1889.
The collection records the rise and fall of Mahone's political career in the 1880s, as well as developments and controversies within the Republican Party in Virginia during this period. In 1888 the Republican Party split into factions which led to rival state conventions and delegations to the national convention. The Mahone defeat of 1889 brought a check to Republican activity in Virginia and in 1893 the Republicans made no effort even to nominate candidates for the governorship or the legislature.
Political allies Mahone cultivated in Virginia are among the chief correspondents. They include Frank S. Blair, Stith Bolling, William E. Cameron, Abram Fulkerson, William Lamb, John E. Massey, John Paul, Harrison Holt Riddleberger, and John S. Wise.
There is very little personal material relating to Mahone or his family. There are a few letters from his son William Mahone, Jr., and in the Subject Files there are several folders of financial receipts representing items bought for the Mahone family.
A Duke University doctoral dissertation was written about Mahone in 1932 by Nelson Morehouse Blake entitled William Mahone of Virginia: Builder, Soldier and Insurgent. It was published in 1935 with the title William Mahone of Virginia, Soldier and Political Insurgent. There are additional Mahone papers in the Mahone-McGill Collection in the Rubenstein Library at the University of Virginia Library in Charlottesville, Virginia.
Subject Headings
Mahone, William, 1826-1895; Electioneering -- Virginia; Elections -- Virginia; Debts, Public -- Virginia; Patronage, Political -- Virginia; Republican Party (Va.); Atlantic, Mississippi and Ohio Railroad Company; Railroads -- Virginia; Blair, Frank Simpson, 1839-1899; Cameron, William Evelyn, 1842-1927; Fulkerson, Abram; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Riddleberger, Harrison Holt, 1844-1890; Paul, John, l839-l901; Bolling, Stith; Wise, John S. (John Sargeant), 1846-1913; Lamb, William, 1835-1909; Voting -- Virginia
Contents of Collection
- Letterbooks, 1866-1893 (bulk 1876-1889), 94 vols. (12 lin. ft.)
  Letterpress books containing copies of Mahone's outgoing letters. Relating chiefly to political matters in Virginia, they concern local and state-wide issues, his work in organizing the Virginia Readjuster Party, his gubernatorial and senatorial campaigns, state conventions, the canvassing of voters before elections, and the appointment of personnel to various governmental offices.
  Other letters deal with railroad policy. Financial matters related to his own railroad, the Atlantic, Mississippi, and Ohio, are mentioned frequently, as are other financial and business interests of Mahone. There are two gaps in the time period covered: 1879, June 19 to 1882, September 1 and 1885, June 29 to September 3.
  Most of the letterbooks contain alphabetical indexes in the front that list the people to whom Mahone was writing. The number beside each name corresponds to the page in the volume where Mahone's letter to that person can be found. In some cases the dates given on the outside of the letterbook are off by a day or so from the dates of letters actually in the letterbook. An effort has been made to specify on the container list the dates of letters actually found in the letterbook, even if they vary slightly from the dates on the cover. Letters are arranged chronologically within each letterbook.
  - 1866 March 15-1866 April 30 (Volume 1)
  - 1866 April 30-1866 September 12 (Volume 2)
  - 1866 October 8-1867 January 14 (Volume 3)
  - 1867 January 14-1867 May 2 (Volume 4)
  - 1867 May 2-1867 July 8 (Volume 5)
  - 1867 July 8-1867 September 7 (Volume 6)
  - 1867 September 15-1867 November 15 (Volume 7)
  - 1867 November 17-1868 January 31 (Volume 8)
  - 1868 February 12-1868 March 30 (Volume 9)
  - 1868 March 29-1868 June 11 (Volume 10)
  - 1868 June 12-1868 September 10 (Volume 11)
  - 1868 September 10-1868 December 21 (Volume 12)
  - 1868 December 21-1869 March 31 (Volume 13)
  - 1869 March 31-1869 September 13 (Volume 14)
  - 1869 September 13-1869 November 29 (Volume 15)
  - 1869 November 29-1870 April 6 (Volume 16)
  - 1870 April 6-1870 December 3 (Volume 17)
  - 1870 December 3-1872 February 26 (Volume 18)
  - 1872 February 28-1873 August 15 (Volume 19)
  - 1873 August 28-1875 January 21 (Volume 20)
  - 1875 January 20-1875 April 22 (Volume 21)
  - 1875 April 22-1876 April 6 (Volume 22)
  - 1876 April 6-1876 June 26 (Volume 23)
  - 1876 June 26-1876 October 16 (Volume 24)
  - 1876 October 19-1877 January 31 (Volume 25)
  - 1877 February 1-1877 June 15 (Volume 26)
  - 1877 June 15-1877 September 15 (Volume 27)
  - 1877 September 15-1877 November 19 (Volume 28)
  - 1877 November 20-1879 May 1 (Volume 29)
  - 1877 May 12-1879 May 3 (Volume 30)
  - 1879 May 1-1879 June 18 (Volume 31)
  - 1882 September 2-1882 October 12 (Volume 32)
  - 1882 October 13-1882 October 23 (Volume 33)
  - 1882 October 23-1882 October 30 (Volume 34)
  - 1882 October 30-1882 December 30 (Volume 35)
  - 1882 December 31-1883 January 19 (Volume 36)
  - 1883 January 19-1883 February 18 (Volume 37)
  - 1883 February 18-1883 March 17 (Volume 38)
  - 1883 March 17-1883 April 6 (Volume 39)
  - 1883 April 6-1883 April 29 (Volume 40)
  - 1883 April 29-1883 June 16 (Volume 41)
  - 1883 June 16-1883 July 13 (Volume 42)
  - 1883 July 13-1883 August 20 (Volume 43)
  - 1883 August 20-1883 September 11 (Volume 44)
  - 1883 September 11-1883 October 5 (Volume 45)
  - 1883 October 5-1883 November 3 (Volume 46)
  - 1883 November 3-1883 December 22 (Volume 47)
  - 1883 December 22-1884 February 11 (Volume 48)
  - 1884 February 12-1884 March 31 (Volume 49)
  - 1884 April 5-1884 June 26 (Volume 50)
  - 1884 June 29-1884 August 30 (Volume 51)
  - 1884 August 30-1884 October 4 (Volume 52)
  - 1884 October 4-1884 November 11 (Volume 53)
  - 1884 November 11-1885 January 5 (Volume 54)
  - 1885 January 5-1885 March 10 (Volume 55)
  - 1885 March 10-1885 May 11 (Volume 56)
  - 1885 May 11-1885 June 11 (Volume 57)
  - 1885 June 12-1885 July 28 (Volume 58)
  - 1885 September 4-1885 September 18 (Volume 59)
  - 1885 September 18-1885 September 29 (Volume 60)
  - 1885 September 28-1885 October 18 (Volume 61)
  - 1885 October 18-1885 October 26 (Volume 62)
  - 1885 October 26-1885 November 24 (Volume 63)
  - 1885 November 25-1886 March 9 (Volume 64)
  - 1886 March 9-1886 May 18 (Volume 65)
  - 1886 May 18-1886 August 13 (Volume 66)
  - 1886 August 16-1886 September 29 (Volume 67)
  - 1886 September 28-1886 November 4 (Volume 68)
  - 1886 November 3-1886 November 28 (Volume 69)
  - 1886 November 30-1887 January 27 (Volume 70)
  - 1887 January 27-1887 March 15 (Volume 71)
  - 1887 March 13-1887 May 15 (Volume 72)
  - 1887 May 14-1887 June 24 (Volume 73)
  - 1887 June 24-1887 August 18 (Volume 74)
  - 1887 August 18-1887 September 5 (Volume 75)
  - 1887 September 5-1887 September 23 (Volume 76)
  - 1887 September 23-1887 October 16 (Volume 77)
  - 1887 October 16-1887 November 7 (Volume 78)
  - 1887 November 7-1887 November 27 (Volume 79)
  - 1887 November 29-1888 January 20 (Volume 80)
  - 1887 January 20-1888 April 4 (Volume 81)
  - 1888 April 4-1888 May 24 (Volume 82)
  - 1888 May 24-1888 August 10 (Volume 83)
  - 1888 August 10-1888 October 6 (Volume 84)
  - 1888 October 7-1888 December 1 (Volume 85)
  - 1888 December 2-1889 January 26 (Volume 86)
  - 1889 January 26-1889 July 25 (Volume 87)
  - 1889 July 27-1889 September 9 (Volume 88)
  - 1889 September 9-1889 October 11 (Volume 89)
  - 1889 October 11-1889 November 19 (Volume 90)
  - 1889 November 18-1890 March 25 (Volume 91)
  - 1890 March 26-1891 March 22 (Volume 92)
  - 1891 March 23-1891 October 31 (Volume 93)
  - 1891 October 31-1893 August 15 (Volume 94)
- Correspondence, 1854-1895 (bulk 1879-1892) and undated, 167 containers (72 lin. ft.)
  This series consists almost entirely of letters sent to Mahone, although there are a few scattered letters from Mahone to others. The most prominently represented topics relate to local and state political matters in Virginia. Among them are the Virginia state debt; rise of the Readjuster movement; Mahone's gubernatorial and senatorial campaigns; canvassing of voters before elections; requests and recommendations for governmental positions; the use of clubs to encourage involvement in politics; and the schism which developed in the Republican Party in Virginia in the late 1880s.
  Other subjects include railroad matters in Virginia, particularly as they concerned the financial issues surrounding the Atlantic, Mississippi, and Ohio Railroad; the Richmond Whig; legislation relating to the taxation of various products such as whiskey and tobacco; and several correspondents' interest in having Mahone serve in Benjamin Harrison's cabinet.
  Many of the letters are numbered on the back and list the name of the letter writer, the date of the letter, a brief summary of the letter's contents, and the place where the letter was written. This information is also preserved in the correspondence indexes. However, not all the correspondence for these years is covered by these volumes. See the description of the Correspondence Indexes below. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - 1854-1859, May, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1869, June-1870, October, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1870, December-1871, December(6 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1872, January-1873, May, (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1873, June-1874, May, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1874, June-1875, September, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1875, October-1876, May 19, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1876, May 20-1876, September, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1876, October-1877, April, (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1877, May 1-1877, June 30, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1877, July 1-1877, July 29, (7 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1877, July 30-1877, December 15, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1877, December 16-1878, June 15, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1878, June 16-1879, February 15, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1879, February 16-1879, August 31, (7 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1879, September 1-1879, November 15, (7 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1879, November 20-1879, December 31, (8 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1880, January 1-1880, March 31, (8 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1880, April 1-1880, June 17, (7 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1880, June 18-1880, July 31, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1880, August 1-1880, September 5, (8 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1880, September 6-1880, October 10, (7 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1880, October 11-1880, November 30, (8 folders) (Box 23)
  - 1880, December 1-1881, January 31, (7 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1881, February 1-1881, March 11, (8 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1881, March 12-1881, March 24, (7 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1881, March 25-1881, April 6, (9 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1881, April 7-1881, April 22, (8 folders) (Box 28)
  - 1881, April 23-1881, May 8, (7 folders) (Box 29)
  - 1881, May 9-1881, May 31, (8 folders) (Box 30)
  - 1881, June 1-1881, June 30, (8 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1881, July 1-1881, July 31, (7 folders) (Box 32)
  - 1881, August 1-1881, August 31, (8 folders) (Box 33)
  - 1881, September 1-1881, September 27, (7 folders) (Box 34)
  - 1881, September 28-1881, October 20, (7 folders) (Box 35)
  - 1881, October 21-1881, November 11, (7 folders) (Box 36)
  - 1881, November 12-1881, November 30, (7 folders) (Box 37)
  - 1881, December 1-1881, December 20, (6 folders) (Box 38)
  - 1881, December 22-1881, December 31, (4 folders) (Box 39)
  - 1882, January 1-1882, January 20, (7 folders) (Box 40)
  - 1882, January 21-1882, February 4, (4 folders) (Box 41)
  - 1882, February 5-1882, February 28, (5 folders) (Box 42)
  - 1882, March 1-1882, March 14, (4 folders) (Box 43)
  - 1882, March 15-1882 March 29, (6 folders) (Box 44)
  - 1882, March 30-1882, April 20, (5 folders) (Box 45)
  - 1882, April 21-1882, May 13, (8 folders) (Box 46)
  - 1882, May 14-1882, May 31, (6 folders) (Box 47)
  - 1882, June 3-1882, June 16, (7 folders) (Box 48)
  - 1882, June 17-1882, June 29, (5 folders) (Box 49)
  - 1882, June 30-1882, July 8, (4 folders) (Box 50)
  - 1882, July 9-1882, July 19, (4 folders) (Box 51)
  - 1882, July 20-1882, July 29, (5 folders) (Box 52)
  - 1882, July 30-1882, August 10, (7 folders) (Box 53)
  - 1882, August 11-1882, August 23, (7 folders) (Box 54)
  - 1882, August 24-1882, September 5, (7 folders) (Box 55)
  - 1882, September 6-1882, September 16, (4 folders) (Box 56)
  - 1882, September 17-1882, September 26, (5 folders) (Box 57)
  - 1882, September 27-1882, October 6, (6 folders) (Box 58)
  - 1882, October 7-1882, October 18, (5 folders) (Box 59)
  - 1882, October 19-1882, October 27, (6 folders) (Box 60)
  - 1882, October 28-1882, November 14, (7 folders) (Box 61)
  - 1882, November 15-1882, December 6, (7 folders) (Box 62)
  - 1882, December 7-1882, December 26, (7 folders) (Box 63)
  - 1882, December 27-1883, January 11, (7 folders) (Box 64)
  - 1883, January 12-1883, January 26, (6 folders) (Box 65)
  - 1883, January 27-1883, February 8, (5 folders) (Box 66)
  - 1883, February 9-1883, February 25, (7 folders) (Box 67)
  - 1883, February 26-1883, March 12, (6 folders) (Box 68)
  - 1883, March 13-1883, March 31, (7 folders) (Box 69)
  - 1883, April 1-1883, April 21, (6 folders) (Box 70)
  - 1883, April 22-1883, May 12, (6 folders) (Box 71)
  - 1883, May 13-1883, May 31, (6 folders) (Box 72)
  - 1883, June 1-1883, June 25, (7 folders) (Box 73)
  - 1883, June 26-1883, July 17, (7 folders) (Box 74)
  - 1883, July 18-1883, August 8, (6 folders) (Box 75)
  - 1883, August 9-1883, August 31, (6 folders) (Box 76)
  - 1883, August-1883, September 17, (6 folders) (Box 77)
  - 1883, September 18-1883, October 2, (6 folders) (Box 78)
  - 1883, October 3-1883, October 16, (5 folders) (Box 79)
  - 1883, October 17-1883, October 31, (5 folders) (Box 80)
  - 1883, November 1-1883, November 22, (7 folders) (Box 81)
  - 1883, November 23-1883, December 20, (7 folders) (Box 82)
  - 1883, December 21-1884, January 12, (7 folders) (Box 83)
  - 1884, January 13-1884, February 4, (7 folders) (Box 84)
  - 1884, February 5-1884, February 29, (7 folders) (Box 85)
  - 1884, March 1-1884, April 21, (7 folders) (Box 86)
  - 1884, April 22-1884, June 14, (6 folders) (Box 87)
  - 1884, June 15-1884, July 19, (5 folders) (Box 88)
  - 1884, July 20-1884, August 31, (6 folders) (Box 89)
  - 1884, September 1-1884, September 30, (5 folders) (Box 90)
  - 1884, October 1-1884, October 24, (5 folders) (Box 91)